A Guide to the WLR Foods digital records, 1948-2002 (bulk 1984-2000)
Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University
Special Collections, James Madison University
WLR Foods digital records1948-2002
Special Collections, James Madison University
2003
645 digital files (5,600 images)
This digital collection contains over 5,000 scanned images representing 645 documents that pertain to the business endeavors, acquisitions, and publications of WLR Foods Incorporated.
WLR Foods Incorporated
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None.
Acquisition Information
Donated by William D. Wampler to Special Collections in February 2008.
Provenance
The current state of the original/physical material used to create the digital scans is unknown. The digital collection was originally divided into seven compact discs titled:
Wampler Foods Historical Records (Scans created between May through November 2005)
Wampler-Longacre Scans, Disc 1 (Scans created between October 25 through November 06 2007)
Wampler-Longacre Scans, Disc 2 (Scans created between June 07 through November 13 2007)
Wampler-Longacre Scans, Disc 3 (Scans created between June 15 through July 17 2007)
Wampler-Longacre Scans, Disc 4 (Scans created between June 16 through September 14 2007)
Wampler-Longacre Scans, Disc 5 (Scans created between September 14 through October 19 2007)
Wampler-Longacre Scans, Disc 6 (Scans created between October 19 through October 24 2007)
The creator or commissioner of the scans is unknown. In December of 2007 the discs were reviewed and appraised by Jeffrey Evans, then President of the Green Valley Auctions, Inc. In February of 2008 William Wampler donated the collection of compact discs to Special Collections. After initial review it was discovered the “Wampler-Longacre Scans, Disc 1” was blank. That same month Mr. Wampler was notified of the error and the “Wampler-Longacre Scans, Disc 1” was replaced with a working disc.
Biographical Information
WLR Foods first incorporated in 1986 and created a holistic and self-sufficient poultry company that was capable of controlling all aspects of poultry production--literally from the egg to the local market. WLR Foods combined hatcheries and farms, feed storage and mills, processing and dressing plants, and distribution under one corporate umbrella. This proved to be a winning combination for the Virginia based company; at the height of its success in 1996, WLR Foods sales reached almost one billion dollars and employed over eight thousand workers. The success achieved by WLR Foods was predicated on three distinct companies that merged in 1986: Wampler Foods, Longacre Farms, and Rockingham Poultry Cooperative.
Wampler Foods began in 1927 with the founding of Wampler Feed and Seed Company. Wampler Feed was the first turkey feed company to contract directly with farms to grow poultry. Under the direction of founder, Charles W. Wampler Sr., Wampler Feed and Seed flourished during the 1930’s, 40’s and 50’s. Wampler Feed revolutionized the poultry industry by pioneering the use of incubators to hatch turkeys and early adoption of cooped turkey growing. Upon the retirement of Charles Wampler Sr., his son, Charles Wampler Jr., took over as manager of Wampler Feed and Seed. In 1969, Wampler Jr. working with Herman Mason joined Wampler Feed with Virginia Valley Processing to create Wampler Foods. The merger brought poultry operations in hatcheries, feeding, growers, and limited processing together into one corporation. Further expansion of processing and increased distribution capabilities fueled the search for subsequent merger opportunities.
During World War II, the American labor force began to diminish. This shortage had a great effect on the agricultural community as farmers and farm workers left to join the war. By 1943, the labor shortage forced Congress to allow draft deferments for farmers and hired men. Horace W. Longacre, a passive Mennonite, sought to serve but not to fight. He considered farm draft deferment a peaceable alternative. In order to qualify for the deferment, Longacre bought 84 acres of farmland in Quakertown, Pennsylvania in 1944 and began selling eggs and vegetables. He soon moved exclusively into poultry operations, processing, and dressing chickens. By 1948, Longacre expanded his business into Virginia and was working with Herman Mason as a feed supplier. Eventually, he moved away from poultry feed and focused entirely on processing. At the peak of his success, Longacre employed over 700 people and continued to further capabilities in dressing and distribution. It was under these circumstances that Longacre’s business became an attractive merger option for Wampler who was seeking to expand in processing. By 1984, the merger was complete and Wampler-Longacre was formed.
The Wampler-Longacre merger set the stage for a new acquisition; in 1986, Wampler-Longacre acquired Rockingham Poultry Cooperative which expanded Wampler-Longacre into chicken production and also set the stage for the formation of WLR Foods Incorporated.
In 1988, WLR Foods hired fortuitously James Keeler as CEO and retained Charles Wampler Jr. as Chairman of the Board. During a hostile takeover attempt by Tyson Foods in 1994, Keeler proved to be a valuable leader in stopping Tyson. The company also went public that year with stock selling on NASDAQ. By the early 1990’s, WLR was packaging poultry into 250 different product lines from hotdogs to burgers. Throughout the 1990’s, WLR Foods continued to expand. In 1990, Golden Acre Foods was acquired along with Cassco Corporation, an ice and cold storage operation. In 1992, Round Hill Foods and the Southern Ice Company were purchased. In 1993, WLR acquired Commonwealth Ice Company and the Beverley Company.
In 1994, Fortune Magazine had listed the company prestigiously in the top 500 companies in the nation. That same year, WLR Foods recorded sales over 700 million and attracted the attention of Tyson Foods Incorporated which attempted a hostile takeover by offering shareholders $30.00 per share which was well above the fair market value at the time. James Keeler, a former lawyer, aggressively fought Tyson Foods by rallying shareholders and using loopholes in Virginia law to prevent a payout from Tyson.
Following the takeover attempt, WLR Foods continued to be a successful leader in the poultry industry and acquired Cuddy Farms Incorporated which strengthened its turkey production and processing operations. However, by 2000 WLR Foods was on the decline with stock shares dropping to $4.59. Pilgrim’s Pride Corporation bought and absorbed WLR Foods thus ending the corporation’s fourteen-year dominance of the industry.
Scope and Content
The WLR Foods digital records, 1948-2002 consists of over 5,000 scanned images. The bulk of the collection is comprised of documents pertaining to WLR Foods Incorporated. The remaining documents relate to Wampler Feed and Seed Company and Wampler Foods and are pre-1984 in date. The 645 documents that make up the collection have been arranged by similar topic and broken down into nine unique series.
Series I: Stock Activities, holds stock reports, NASDAQ market reports, and letters to stockholders of WLR Foods. The majority of this collection spans a nine-year period from 1991 to 2000. Two documents in Series I cover the stock activities of Wampler Foods from 1976 and 1979. Also included is a letter written to WLR Foods shareholders regarding the hostile takeover attempt by Tyson Foods. This series contains 175 documents.
Series II: Meetings and Minutes, comprises minutes from Board of Directors meetings, Shareholder meetings, and WLR Foods Executive Committee meetings. The majority of this series spans 1985 to 2000 and contains 157 documents.
Series III: Financial Reports, includes financial statements from 1955 to 2000. The reports relate to the Wampler-Bryan Company, Wampler Foods, Golden Acre Foods, Wampler-Longacre, and WLR Foods. Of the 85 documents in the series, 34 report on the finances of WLR Foods’ many subsidiaries. The bulk of this collection ranges from 1989 to 2000 and details the quarterly reports of WLR Foods. Also included are eleven of the company’s annual reports.
Series IV: Publications contains WLR Foods’ annual newsletter, “Dimensions.” These newsletters were distributed primarily to employees and community members. They document the company’s growth and history and feature spotlights on employees. One publication which predates WLR Foods is a document titled: “Eat More Turkey” by David W. Evans in 1960. The majority of this 68 document series dates from 1988 to 2002 with some publications as early as November 1984.
Series V: Acquisitions, Mergers, and Takeovers includes documents from the merger between Wampler Foods in Longacre Farms in 1984, acquisitions by WLR Foods of other companies such as Cuddy and Cassco Ice, several documents on the hostile takeover attempt by Tyson Foods in 1994/1995, and the buy out of WLR by Pilgrim’s Pride in 2000. This series spans 1984 to 2000 and contains 58 documents.
Series VI: Announcements, Memos, and News details company announcements and memos such as new chairman elections. Additionally, news and press releases on topics such as quarterly reports, and company endeavors are also included here. Then president of WLR, James Keeler, released two news reports to shareholders panning the hostile takeover attempt of Tyson Foods in 1994. This series contains 44 items and covers the years 1987 to 2000.
Series VII: Audit and Examination Reports deals entirely with the separate companies that eventually merged to create WLR Foods. The series begins in 1948 with a report on examination from Wampler Feed and Seed Company. Other companies included in this series are Wampler Foods and Virginia Valley Processors. Each of the examination accounts for the business’ balance sheets and were conducted by certified public accountants from Harrisonburg Virginia. The specific accountants vary from year to year. 39 documents make up this collection with the bulk of material spanning 1958 to 1978.
Series VIII: Various Documents includes multiple types of company publications such as four iterations of WLR Foods philosophy, by-laws, expenditure requests, and a notification of Wampler-Longacre changing brand name to Wampler. There are 22 documents in this series that covers the years 1987 to 1996.
Series IX: Correspondence is the smallest of the nine series, totals eight documents, and spans the years 1988 to 1991. The correspondence varies between WLR Foods’ several subsidiaries.
Arrangement
The size or number of items in the given series arranges the nine series in this collection. Series I being the largest and comprised of 175 items, and Series IX being the smallest with 8 items. Items are arranged in chronological order within each series. Each document that does not have a known date associated with it is listed as undated in the date field and placed at the end of the series.
Series creation and chronological arrangement were imposed during processing due to the absence of a clear original order. Because the collection is solely digital, there are no box or folder numbers associated with the items. To access the digital images that represent the physical documents, a researcher will need the series number, item title, and corresponding date.
The arrangement of series is as follows:
I: Stock Activities, 1976-2000, bulk 1991-2000.
II: Meetings and Minutes, 1970-2001, bulk 1985-2000.
III: Financial Reports, 1955-2000, bulk 1989-2000.
IV: Publications, 1979-2002, bulk 1988-2002.
V: Acquisitions, Mergers, and Takeovers, 1984-2000, bulk 1984-1995.
VI: Announcements, Memos, and News, 1987-2000, bulk 1992-1999.
VII: Audit and Examination Reports, 1948-1978, bulk 1958-1978.
VIII: Various Documents, 1987-1996, bulk 1988.
IX: Correspondence, 1988-1991.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Bibliography
Chintala, David Michael. Correlation between export sales and stock price. Harrisonburg: James Madison University, 1997.
Fife, Tom. Activity-based costing systems and their applications in the poultry industry. Harrisonburg: James Madison University, 1993.
Whiteley, Laura E., "WLR Foods, Inc." In International Directory of Company Histories Vol. 21, 1998, edited by Tina Grant, and Jay P. Pederson, 534-536. Detroit: St. James Press, 1998.
Related Material
Wampler Business Records, SC# 5024
Wampler, Charles W., Jr. Collection, SC# 3095
Elizabeth "Libby" Custer Collection, SC# 2002
Contents List
- Stock Activities, 1976-2000, bulk 1991-2000, (175 items)
  - Stock Activity, 1976
  - Stock Activity, February 1979
  - Letter to Stockholders of Rockingham Poultry Inc., August 11 1987
  - Wampler-Longacre-Rockingham, Inc. - Memo of Federal Securities L, 1988
  - NASDAQ Report, January 1989
  - NASDAQ Report, August 1989
  - Wheat First: Butcher & Singer notice of WLR decline in sales and stock rating, August 23 1991
  - Summary of Activity, WLR Foods, Inc. (printed by NASDAQ Stock Market), September 1991
  - Summary of Activity, WLR Foods, Inc. (printed by NASDAQ Stock Market) [Confidential], October 1991
  - A.G. Edwards & Son Inc. Stock Report, October 1991
  - Stock Reports, December 1991
  - Stock Reports, December 1991
  - Description of Convertible Cumulative Perpetual Preferred Stock, Series L, December 02 1991
  - Order of Presentations regarding proposal to repurchase Longacre Shares, December 03 1991
  - Stock Reports, January 1992
  - Stock Reports, January 1992
  - Stock Reports, February 1992
  - Stock Reports, March 1992
  - Stock Reports, March 1992
  - Stock Reports, April 1992
  - Stock Reports, April 1992
  - Stock Reports, April 1992
  - Stock Reports, May 1992
  - Stock Reports, June 1992
  - Stock Reports, July 1992
  - Stock Reports, July 1992
  - Stock Reports, August 1992
  - Stock Reports, August 1992
  - Stock Reports, September 1992
  - Stock Reports, September 1992
  - Stock Reports, October 1992
  - Stock Reports, December 1992
  - Stock Reports, January 1993
  - Stock Reports, January 1993
  - Stock Reports, January 1993
  - Stock Reports, February 1993
  - Stock Reports, March 1993
  - Stock Activity, April 1993
  - Stock Reports, April 1993
  - Stock Activity, May 1993
  - Stock Activity, May 1993
  - Stock Reports, May 1993
  - Stock Activity, June 1993
  - Stock Activity, July 1993
  - Stock Activity, July 1993
  - Stock Activity, August 1993
  - Stock Activity, August 1993
  - Stock Activity, September 1993
  - Stock Activity, October 1993
  - Stock Activity, October 1993
  - Stock Activity, October 1993
  - Stock Activity, December 1993
  - Stock Activity, January 1994
  - Stock Activity, January-February 1994
  - WLR Foods, Inc. - Letter to Shareholders regarding Tyson, 1994
  - Stock Activity, February 1994
  - Stock Activity, February-March 1994
  - Stock Activity, March 1994
  - Stock Activity, March 1994
  - Stock Activity, April 1994
  - Stock Activity, May 1994
  - Stock Activity, June 1994
  - Stock Activity, July 1994
  - Stock Activity, August 1994
  - Stock Activity, August 1994
  - Stock Activity, September 1994
  - Stock Activity, October 1994
  - Stock Activity, October 1994
  - Stock Reports, October 1994
  - Stock Reports, October 1994
  - Stock Reports, November 1994
  - Stock Reports, November 1994
  - Stock Reports, December 1994
  - Stock Reports, December 1994
  - Stock Reports, January 1995
  - Stock Reports, January 1995
  - Stock Reports, January 1995
  - WLR Foods, Inc. - Summary of Stock Activity, 1995
  - Stock Reports, February 1995
  - Stock Reports, February 1995
  - Stock Reports, February 1995
  - Stock Reports, March 1995
  - Stock Reports, March 1995
  - Stock Reports, April 1995
  - Stock Reports, April 1995
  - Stock Reports, May 1995
  - Stock Reports, May 1995
  - Stock Reports, June 1995
  - Stock Reports, July 1995
  - Stock Reports, August 1995
  - Stock Reports, September 1995
  - Stock Reports, October 1995
  - Stock Reports, November 1995
  - Stock Reports, November 1995
  - Stock Reports, December 1995
  - Stock Reports, January 1996
  - Stock Reports, February 1996
  - Stock Reports, March 1996
  - Stock Reports, April 1996
  - Stock Reports, May 1996
  - Stock Reports, May 1996
  - Stock Reports, June 1996
  - Stock Reports, July 1996
  - Stock Reports, August 1996
  - Stock Reports, August 1996
  - Stock Reports, September 1996
  - Stock Reports, September 1996
  - Stock Reports, October 1996
  - Stock Reports, November 1996
  - Stock Reports, December 1996
  - Stock Reports, December 1996
  - Stock Reports, January 1997
  - Stock Reports, February 1997
  - Stock Reports, February 1997
  - Stock Reports, March 1997
  - Stock Reports, March 1997
  - Stock Reports, March 1997
  - Stock Reports, April 1997
  - Stock Reports, June 1997
  - Stock Reports, July 1997
  - Stock Reports, August 1997
  - Stock Reports, September 1997
  - Stock Reports, October 1997
  - Stock Reports, November 1997
  - Stock Reports, December 1997
  - Stock Reports, January 1998
  - Stock Reports, February 1998
  - Stock Reports, February 1998
  - Stock Reports, March 1998
  - Stock Reports, March 1998
  - Stock Reports, April 1998
  - Stock Reports, May 1998
  - Stock Reports, June 1998
  - Stock Reports, June 1998
  - Stock Reports, July 1998
  - Stock Reports, August 1998
  - Stock Reports, September 1998
  - Stock Reports, October 1998
  - Stock Reports, November 1998
  - Stock Reports, December 1998
  - Stock Reports, January 1999
  - Stock Reports, February 1999
  - Stock Reports, March 1999
  - Stock Reports, March 1999
  - Stock Reports, May 1999
  - Stock Reports, May 1999
  - Stock Reports, June 1999
  - Stock Reports, July 1999
  - Stock Reports, August 1999
  - Stock Reports, September 1999
  - Stock Reports, October 1999
  - Stock Reports, October 1999
  - Stock Reports, October 1999
  - Stock Reports, November 1999
  - Stock Reports, December 1999
  - Stock Reports, January 2000
  - Stock Reports, January 2000
  - Stock Reports, 2000
  - Stock Reports, February 2000
  - Stock Reports, February 2000
  - Stock Reports, March 2000
  - Stock Reports, March 2000
  - Stock Reports, April 2000
  - Stock Reports, May 2000
  - Stock Reports, June 2000
  - Stock Reports, July 2000
  - Stock Reports, August 2000
  - Stock Reports, September 2000
  - Stock Reports, October 2000
  - Stock Reports, October 2000
  - Stock Reports, November 2000
  - Stock Reports, November 2000
  - Stock Reports, December 2000
  - Stock Reports, undated
- Meetings and Minutes, 1970-2001, bulk 1985-2000, (157 items)
  - Minutes of Director's Meetings, including many management & Board decisions, 1970-1975
  - Minutes of Director's Meetings, including many management & Board decisions, July 1984-June 1985
  - Minutes of Director's Meetings, including many management & Board decisions, February 1985
  - Minutes of Director's Meetings, including many management & Board decisions, March 1985
  - Minutes of Director's Meetings, including many management & Board decisions, April 1985
  - Minutes of Director's Meetings, including many management & Board decisions, May 1985
  - Minutes of Director's Meetings, including many management & Board decisions, June 1985
  - Minutes of Director's Meetings, including many management & Board decisions, June 1985
  - Minutes of Director's Meetings, including many management & Board decisions, August 1985
  - Minutes of Director's Meetings, including many management & Board decisions, September 1985
  - Minutes of Director's Meetings, including many management & Board decisions, December 1985
  - Minutes of Director's Meetings, including many management & Board decisions, February 1986
  - Minutes of Director's Meetings, including many management & Board decisions, March 1986
  - Minutes of Director's Meetings, including many management & Board decisions, April 1986
  - Minutes of Director's Meetings, including many management & Board decisions, June 1986
  - Minutes of Director's Meetings, including many management & Board decisions, September 1986
  - Minutes of Director's Meetings, including many management & Board decisions, October 1986
  - Minutes of Director's Meetings, including many management & Board decisions, October 1986
  - Wampler-Longacre, Inc. - Stockholders Meetings, 1987
  - W-L, Inc. Board of Directors Meeting, March 30 1987
  - W-L, Inc. Executive Committee Meeting, April 21 1987
  - W-L, Inc. Executive Committee Meeting, May 28 1987
  - W-L, Inc. Board of Directors Meeting, June 23 1987
  - W-L, Inc. Executive Committee Meeting, July 28 1987
  - Special Stockholder's Meeting, September 15 1987
  - W-L, Inc. Board of Directors Meeting, September 15 1987
  - Wampler Foods, Inc. Board of Directors Meeting, November 13 1987
  - W-L, Inc. Board of Directors Meeting, December 15 1987
  - W-L, Inc. Board of Directors Meeting, December 16 1986
  - Wampler-Longacre-Rockingham, Inc. - Board of Directors Meeting, 1988
  - Wampler-Longacre-Rockingham, Inc. - Meeting of Shareholders Proxy, 1988
  - WLR Foods, Inc. - Board of Directors Organizational Meeting, 1988
  - WLR, Inc. Board of Directors Meeting, January 7 1988
  - WLR, Inc. Board of Directors Meeting [Organizational Meeting], January 7 1988
  - WLR, Inc. Executive Committee Meeting [special meeting], February 23 1988
  - WLR, Inc. Executive Committee Meeting, April 21 1988
  - WLR, Inc. Board of Directors Meeting, March 22 1988
  - WLR, Inc. Executive Committee Meeting, March 22 1988
  - WLR, Inc. Executive Committee Meeting [Agenda], May 2 1988
  - WLR, Inc. Executive Committee Meeting, May 17 1988
  - WLR, Inc. Board of Directors Meeting, June 28 1988
  - WLR, Inc. Joint Meeting, August 23 1988
  - WLR, Inc. Executive Committee Meeting, September 27 1988
  - Board of Directors Meeting Minutes, November 1 1988
  - Wampler-Longacre-Rockingham, Inc. Annual Shareholder's Meeting, November 1 1988
  - WLR Foods, Inc. - Meeting of Shareholders Proxy, 1989
  - WLR Foods, Inc. - Shareholders Meeting Report, 1989
  - Joint Meeting of the Board of Directors and Executive Committee, March 28 1989
  - WLR Foods, Inc. Executive Committee Meeting, April 18 1989
  - WLR Foods, Inc. Executive Committee Meeting, June 27 1989
  - WLR Foods, Inc. Board of Directors Meeting Minutes, July 25 1989
  - WLR Foods, Inc. Board of Directors Meeting Minutes, August 22 1989
  - WLR Foods, Inc. Executive Committee Meeting, September 26 1989
  - WLR Foods, Inc. Board of Directors Meeting, October 23 1989-October 24 1989
  - WLR Agenda for Shareholders Meeting, October 24 1989
  - WLR Foods, Inc. Board of Directors Meeting Minutes, December 19 1989
  - WLR Foods, Inc. Executive Committee Meeting, December 20 1989
  - WLR Foods, Inc. - Annual Board Organizational Meeting, 1990
  - WLR Foods, Inc. - Annual Shareholders Meeting, 1990
  - WLR Foods, Inc. - Board of Directors Organizational Meeting, 1990
  - WLR Foods, Inc. - Meeting of Board of Directors, 1990
  - WLR Foods, Inc. - Meeting of Shareholders Proxy, 1990
  - WLR Foods, Inc. Board of Directors Meeting Minutes, February 27 1990
  - WLR Foods, Inc. Board of Directors Meeting Minutes, April 26 1990
  - WLR Foods, Inc. Board of Directors Meeting Minutes, June 26 1990
  - WLR Foods, Inc. Board of Directors Meeting Minutes, August 28 1990
  - Animal Health & Specialties, Inc. Shareholder's Meeting Minutes, October 9 1990
  - WLR Foods, Inc. Board of Directors Meeting Minutes, October 20 1990
  - WLR Foods, Inc. Board of Directors Meeting Minutes, December 18 1990
  - WLR Foods, Inc. - Annual Board Organizational Meeting, 1991
  - WLR Foods, Inc. - Meeting of Shareholders Proxy, 1991
  - WLR Foods, Inc. Board of Directors Meeting Minutes, February 26 1991
  - WLR Foods, Inc. Board of Directors Meeting Minutes, April 26 1991
  - WLR Foods, Inc. Board of Directors Meeting Minutes, June 21 1991
  - WLR Foods, Inc. Board of Directors Meeting Minutes [Confidential], August 27 1991